<spec>

<front>
  <title>MathML Web Profile</title>
  <editors>David Carlisle and Frédéric Wang</editors>
  <status>
   <p>Just experimenting...</p>
  </status>
</front>
<abstract>
 <p>Mostly just experimenting with structure.....</p>

 <p>This document is a detailed technical document for a core subset of presentation
MathML <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx11" title="">MathML3</a>]</cite> in order to render with high quality the majority of
mathematical formulas used in practice.
This document should be understandable by any implementer with
sufficient knowledge of web rendering engines and text layout.
Contrary to the official MathML specification, a significant effort is made to
be as accurate as possible on the visual rendering of mathematical formulas
using additional rules from the TeXBook’s Appendix G <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx16" title="">TeXBook</a>]</cite> and from
the Open Font Format version 3 <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx13" title="">OpenFontFormat3</a>]</cite>.
The priority is to be compatible with existing technologies of web
rendering engines <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx9" title="">HTML5</a>]</cite> by relying as much as possible on CSS, text &amp;
table layout and box models. As a consequence, parts of presentation MathML
that do not fit well in this framework or are rarely used in practice
have been ommited ; details on these and suggestions for standardization bodies
are provided in the appendix.</p>

</abstract>

<minh file="S1"/>
<minh file="S2"/>
<minh file="S3"/>
<minh file="A1"/>
<minh file="A2"/>
<minh file="A3"/>
<minh file="A4"/>
<section id="rnc">
 <h1>Relax NG</h1>
 <p>This section displays a non-normative Relax NG Schema which
 details the elements and attributes defined by this specification.
 Note that MathML does not need to be expressed in XML syntax, in
 particular the syntax defined by HTML may be used. However this
 schema may be taken as an informal specification of the structure,
 whatever syntax is used.</p>
 
 <rnc file="mathml4-web.rnc"/>
 
</section>
</spec>
