<!DOCTYPE html><html>
<head>
<title>1 Introduction‣ MathML in HTML5 - Implementation Note</title>

<meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=UTF-8"/>

</head>
<body>
<section id="introduction">
<h1>
<span>1 </span>Introduction</h1>
<div></div>

<section id="rationale">
<h2><span>1.1 </span>Rationale for this Technical Document</h2>

<div id="SS1.p1">
<p><span>This section is non-normative.</span></p>
</div>
<div id="SS1.p2">
<p>The Mathematical Markup Language is the most popular XML format for describing
mathematical notation and capturing both its structure and content
<cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx11" title="">MathML3</a>]</cite>. It has been integrated in various other standards such as
<cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx9" title="">HTML5</a>]</cite>, <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx8" title="">EPUB3</a>]</cite>, <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx12" title="">ODF1</a>]</cite> or <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx5" title="">Daisy3</a>]</cite>. Although
the stated goal is “to enable mathematics to be served, received, and
processed on the World Wide Web”, the MathML specification has
two serious shortcomings that make it hard to implement presentation MathML in
web rendering engines:</p>
</div>
<div id="SS1.p3">
<ol id="I1">
<li id="I1.i1">
<div id="I1.i1.p1">
<p><span>The MathML specification intentionally does not contain any detailed
rendering rules</span>. As a consequence, the fact that web rendering engines are
compliant with the MathML specification does not necessarily mean that they
will have the rendering quality expected by most readers.
For example, the specification essentially just says that
“mfrac element is used for fractions” and that the default medium
linethickness “is left up to the rendering agent” <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx11" title="">MathML3</a>]</cite>.
As a comparison, to determine the exact spacing and thickness of
fractions and stacks the
TeXBook’s Appendix G <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx16" title="">TeXBook</a>]</cite> relies
on parameters <math id="I1.i1.p1.m1" alttext="\sigma_{8},\sigma_{9},\xi_{8},{3\xi_{8}},{7\xi_{8}},\sigma_{11}" display="inline"><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>σ</mi><mn>8</mn></msub><mo>,</mo><msub><mi>σ</mi><mn>9</mn></msub><mo>,</mo><msub><mi>ξ</mi><mn>8</mn></msub><mo>,</mo><mrow><mn>3</mn><mo>⁢</mo><msub><mi>ξ</mi><mn>8</mn></msub></mrow><mo>,</mo><mrow><mn>7</mn><mo>⁢</mo><msub><mi>ξ</mi><mn>8</mn></msub></mrow><mo>,</mo><msub><mi>σ</mi><mn>11</mn></msub></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">\sigma_{8},\sigma_{9},\xi_{8},{3\xi_{8}},{7\xi_{8}},\sigma_{11}</annotation></semantics></math> and
<math id="I1.i1.p1.m2" alttext="\sigma_{12}" display="inline"><semantics><msub><mi>σ</mi><mn>12</mn></msub><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">\sigma_{12}</annotation></semantics></math> while the MATH table of the Open Font Format
<cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx13" title="">OpenFontFormat3</a>]</cite> extends these to parameters
<code>FractionNumeratorDisplayStyleShiftUp</code>,
<code>FractionNumeratorShiftUp</code>,
<code>FractionNumeratorDisplayStyleGapMin</code>,
<code>FractionNumeratorGapMin</code>,
<code>FractionRuleThickness</code>,
<code>FractionDenominatorDisplayStyleGapMin</code>,
<code>FractionDenominatorGapMin</code>,
<code>FractionDenominatorDisplayStyleShiftDown</code>,
<code>FractionDenominatorShiftDown</code>,
<code>StackTopDisplayStyleShiftUp</code>,
<code>StackTopShiftUp</code>,
<code>StackDisplayStyleGapMin</code>,
<code>StackGapMin</code>,
<code>StackBottomDisplayStyleShiftDown</code> and
<code>StackBottomShiftDown</code>.</p>
</div>
</li>
<li id="I1.i2">
<div id="I1.i2.p1">
<p><span>The MathML specification is designed as an independent
XML language and browser vendors have almost not been involved in the
standardization process</span>,
except for integration in <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx9" title="">HTML5</a>]</cite>.
Instead, the specification is sometimes biased by MathML rendering and
authoring tools behaving quite differently from web rendering engines.
Hence it is not always obvious whether all features are fundamental or
whether they fit well into the web rendering engine codebase.
For example, the <span>&lt;mfenced&gt;</span> element is just a
“convenient form in which to express common constructs involving fences”
but is strictly equivalent to an expanded form with <span>&lt;mrow&gt;</span> and
<span>&lt;mo&gt;</span> elements. It requires web rendering engines
to create many “anonymous”
rendering frames and keep them up-to-date, to duplicate the logic
for drawing and exposing the content of fenced expressions etc.
Another example is the first cell in a
<span>&lt;mlabeledtr&gt;</span> row which is not necessarily positioned the same way as
in HTML table and actually is supposed not to be involved in metric
computation or border drawing of the table <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx11" title="">MathML3</a>]</cite>.</p>
</div>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
<div id="SS1.p4">
<p>This “MathML in HTML5” implementation note intends to address these issues by
being as accurate as
possible on the visual rendering of mathematical formulas using additional
rules from the TeXBook’s Appendix G <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx16" title="">TeXBook</a>]</cite> and from
the Open Font Format <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx13" title="">OpenFontFormat3</a>]</cite>.
Focus has been put on keeping compatible with existing technologies of web
rendering engines <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx9" title="">HTML5</a>]</cite> by relying as much as possible on CSS, text &amp;
table layout and box models. As a consequence, parts of presentation MathML
that do not fit well in this framework or are rarely used in practice
have been ommited ; details on these and suggestions for standardization bodies
are provided in the Appendix.</p>
</div>
<div id="SS1.p5">
<p>Future versions of this document may describe support for a larger subset
of presentation MathML by including features that are important in a web context
e.g. CSS-compatible line breaking.</p>
</div>
</section>
<section id="rem1">
<h2><span>1.2 </span>Remarks</h2>

<div id="SS2.p1">
<p><span>This section is non-normative.</span></p>
</div>
<div id="SS2.p2">
<p>This document focuses on the most important points to implement
MathML in web rendering engines. Hence it is intentionally short and readers are
invited to check the MathML 3 specification for details <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx11" title="">MathML3</a>]</cite>.
As a convenience, quotations from the MathML 3 specification are referred to
with the following style:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>This is a quotation from the MathML 3 specification.</p>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div id="SS2.p3">
<p>This document relies on many definitions taken from the MATH specification
of the Open Font Format <cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx13" title="">OpenFontFormat3</a>]</cite>. These values are written with
the following style:
<span>This is a definition from the MATH specification</span>.</p>
</div>
<div id="SS2.p4">
<p>This document only deals with the visual rendering of presentation MathML
and briefly mentions interactions (javascript, links etc). It does not specify
how presentation MathML must be exposed to assitive technologies nor does it
explain how the semantic provided by content MathML can be used.</p>
</div>
<div id="SS2.p5">
<p>This document 
should be read in a browser that supports web technologies
such as HTML, CSS, SVG and MathML.</p>
</div>
<div id="SS2.p6">
<p>A <a href="http://www.w3c-test.org/mathml/" title="">set of tests</a>
following the format and convention of the
<a href="http://testthewebforward.org/" title="">Test The Web Forward project</a>
are available in a separate
<a href="https://github.com/w3c/web-platform-tests/tree/master/mathml" title="">git repository</a>.
Browser vendors are encouraged to use these tests during
implementation &amp; automated testing. Contribution of new tests and error reports
are welcome.</p>
</div>
</section>
<section id="terminology">
<h2>
<span>1.3 </span>Terminology</h2>

<div id="SS3.p1">
<p>The key words MUST, MUST NOT, REQUIRED, SHALL, SHALL NOT, SHOULD, SHOULD NOT,
RECOMMENDED, MAY, and OPTIONAL, are to be interpreted as described in
<cite>[<a href="bib.html#bibx10" title="">IETFRFC2119</a>]</cite>.</p>
</div>
</section>
</section>
</body>
</html>
